[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Jeff dittle I'm
excited to invite Orie sapora as our
guest on the show today for a
conversation about the role of the
software architect ory support a
co-founded V function and serves as its
system architect prior to founding V
function Ori was the lead systems
architect of watch dooc until its
acquisition by Blackberry where he
continued to serve in the role of
distinguished systems architect ory has
a BS and Computer Engineering and an MS
in computer science from Tel Aviv
University Orie welcome to the show
thank you Jeff thank you for having the
role of software architect that's a
pretty broad area for discussion so
let's start with something specific what
do you feel is one of the most important
aspects of the role of software
architect that maybe is often
misunderstood or overlooked a lot of
people are under the misconception that
design and the role of the architect is
something that happens at the beginning
of an application life
cycle and I really can't think of a more
erroneous assumption because software is
a living breathing thing and as it
changes the design must always adapt and
has to go with the flow sort of and so
the architect must always be in there
within that life cycle to help guide and
make the necessary changes into the
architecture and design of the system to
make sure that it can adapt and over
time acquire new features new
Integrations which is really the goal of
of continuing develop an application so
are you seeing situations where
companies are trying to say the
architect does some design work up front
and then maybe they just move to another
team or they disappear I have actually
also with our current with some of our
current clients where there is a maybe a
group of Architects and they will be
handed down like the doc stage of of a a
new feature and they design it they
maybe do a prototype they that hated
over and they lose any control but it's
not only a matter of control they don't
have actually visibility into what's
happened with that was it a good design
you know maybe it wasn't the best design
maybe we need to do another iteration of
the design to adapt to something that we
didn't figure out in the beginning and
it's difficult to get everything right
the first time and that's even with the
first iteration of an implementation and
of course things change over time a new
feature might influence an older design
because it's the right way to it was the
right way to go before isn't necessarily
the right way to go now so what are the
consequences when you see this happening
on projects when somebody just does some
design and then they sort of disappear
and they're no longer available what is
the impact on the software project that
you see so I can think of the impact
from two directions one would be the
software itself I think the software
becomes less organized possibly more
complex we can talk about acquiring
technical debt I think those are all
kind of synonyms right complex software
software tracking go that and from the
point of view of the architect and the
architect now is moving on to the next
thing now they're a new
POC and I think they're lacking that
sense of accountability
that you can take pride in your design
and see it come to fruition and then
make sure that it changes over time as
is required and you have difficulty
doing that when you're not in that flow
of changes do you run into Architects
that maybe don't want that
accountability perhaps is that possibly
part of the problem I'm sure there are
I'm sure these exist I have to say I
don't think that's the problem I mean
nobody starts as being an architect
we're not in the construction business
so I think Architects are
developers and they're developers that
actually were looking for more
accountability and looking to have more
of a say in how things work and if they
have inquisitive minds they want to
solve problems and then when they get
removed from the situation I don't think
I think they do they say okay cool I
have a new problem to solve I don't
think they necessarily want that to be
the case right so what's the cause then
because I I've seen this too and I
imagine many of our listeners has seen
this as well and maybe not every company
functions this way and we're certainly
trying not to where I work but what do
you see as the cause of this Architects
do some design do pcc's they do some
exploratory work and then they move on
like where's that coming from I have
some recollection of it being different
the waterfall era oh you said the W word
okay interesting well yes so so share
your recollection because that's kind of
a straw man that often gets stood up and
beat up but okay so it's different then
I'm not saying I miss it okay oh but it
was it was different because it was very
clear what was the Architects or system
engineer role so you had this period of
time where you were the king you like
okay we're done with in requirements now
we're at design phase and you work on
the design and you work with others on
the design and at the end like you hand
the stick over to the implementation
team but then you keep working on the
now now you're in the next Cadence right
next version but you're already in the
next version and you're following
through on the implementation and next
version of the same software and over
time with what is called agile although
I'm not sure it's called agile for a
good reason what happened is we kind of
May design something that is nice to
have as opposed to a very big must in
the
process and since it's nice to have then
I don't have to involve the architect or
even the design knowhow at every point
of the process I invoke my own design
knowhow right as a developer
as a team lead I own everything as a
team lead and it's my responsibility
it's nobody else's and then there's the
architect he's kind of a consultant now
I like to think of it in a mob family in
The Godfather movies there's a
consiliary yes he's kind of he's sitting
there next to the boss and he's
whispering in his ear so okay that's the
architect but then he doesn't do any of
the
damage interesting
maybe it's a bit of a violent but I'm
thinking about movies right not
real well back to Waterfall and agile so
you know first off and we don't want to
go into this because this isn't the
conversation about waterfall but you
know that this is one of those things
too where people who didn't experience
it maybe have some false assumptions
about how it actually worked so were
there shops who did all their design up
front and all the requirements all their
design you were never allowed to touch
it there were some that's not what most
people did and we've gone full circle
now as you're describing you know agile
and of course there's some questions
about is agile really giving us agility
which is something we can talk about but
it reminds me of the phrase big design
up front which is what people think
waterfall was and then it sounds like
what you're saying the far extreme is no
design up front or no design at all or
no design ever okay yeah okay so how do
we strike the balance there between
these things well first make a case for
design why do we need design we need to
plan
and we need to give thought into what
we're doing we need to think okay that's
good we need to think you can call it
whatever you like right we can call it
design but we can call it just stopping
to smell the roses or just stopping you
know if we go from I'm coding this
feature and then I'm coding the next
feature and no point that I give thought
into how certain components interact
with each other how they affect each
other how the new feature I'm going to
write is going to affect the previous
features I've written and the future
features that I haven't even thought
about yet we have to think about that if
we don't what happens is that when we
get to the new next feature we don't
know where to start and or we just break
everything all the time because we never
given anything any thought so there's no
like specific design methodology I'm
going to say we have to do this other
than that but you have to stop and think
and plan I mean you don't have to but
how's that working for
you I'm sure some people will say I've
never planned and it's everything is
perfect but I would think that these
people are very Unique Individuals and
we can't all be like that some people
are that good I accept that but we're
not all like that or maybe they're just
that lucky so it sounds like your
contention then is that design is an on
going task not a task we just do up
front and it's not a task that we just
don't do at all it's an ongoing process
yes absolutely and that it's the role of
the software architect to either own
this process participate in this process
what I think they own it but not own in
the sense that they're they're
definitely not the only ones doing it
it's important everybody does design
it's important because that sense of
ownership we all also want every
developer to feel ownership on what they
did otherwise they're basically gen and
nobody wants that we have and now we
even have gen right I would have said
that two years ago without having gen
said they're like robots but now we
actually have robots right in C nobody
wants developers to be robots they want
to have ownership into what they did and
ownership comes from the ability to make
decisions can't have ownership if
they're just following a script
so let's talk about the path that most
people follow to architect and then I
want to explore a little bit about your
path which I understand is a little bit
different in your experience where do
most software architect or people with
the title right software architect
what's the typical career path that
leads them to that position in a company
and maybe if there's any benefits to it
and maybe any challenges or problems
with with how it typically comes about
from your perspective I mostly think
about suffer Architects as individual
contributors when you start as a
developer in corporation organization or
just in your professional life you start
at the bottom I think we all start at
the bottom and we are just programmers
developers engineers and we learn the
craft and as we do we get hopefully
better at it and then your career path
is either going being a better
individual contributor or being a
manager and so people who who have
chosen to be individual contributors
then have a decision to make they can
become very specialized in some
methodology or some
technology or they can become very good
backend developers and very quick or
they see themselves as people taking a
bit of a bird's eye view and then they
would be drawn into software
architecture more so once we identify
that as individuals it will like to
start a Pursuit that we start reading
stuff and then eventually go up to
somebody and say Hey I want to roll the
software AR and voila hopefully you get
it just by asking it took me a couple of
them so you reached this point and most
of what you described sounds to me like
technical
leadership but is software architect to
just the dev who's been doing it longer
or I mean it's kind of a leading
question but like distinguish a little
bit you know in your mind because I
think you're saying there's more to it
than just well I've been a developer for
20 years and I've read some things and
now I suddenly am just made software
architect which may happen but you know
maybe there's some problems with that
too I think it's a matter of choice of
what you're interested in because if
you're just interested in the technology
then it wouldn't appeal to you or it
shouldn't appeal to you I would say you
should be interested in the meantion of
a system and complex systems and it
really comes down to what do you care
about what is your passion my passion
was to see how everything works together
and to help Drive Integrations between
components and systems and people and
thirdparty software and first party
software and everything coming together
and to be able to give feedback to the
product and break down product
requirements and all of that is not
something that comes with being a good
developer but I think it's a baseline
you have to be a good developer but you
have to have the passion
for that system engineering way of
thinking the architecture way of
thinking like you should be able to go
from 30,000 ft to level and if you don't
I'm not sure that's the role for you you
should want to yeah so basically the
architect has a more comprehensive view
of how things fit together how things
can integrate how they should integrate
at a high level they need to understand
the technology but then they also need
to have the bigger picture in mind
that's a broad summary but is that
effectively the general concept that
you're describing yeah I think we we're
getting a bit into what is the role and
what's it made of I think Architects
eventually are decision
makers and their decision makers you can
say everybody's a decision maker and
it's the just a matter of what type of
decisions they make but they decision
makers on the level of solving problems
they're presented with a problem by
someone who is usually less technical
than they are and they need to break
down that problem and breaking down that
problem is into some sort of technical
language I think we're familiar with
that how and what kind of recursion
right cascading waterfall of how and
what so I would think of the software
architect as the first person that hears
the how which is the what sorry that's
not Technical and breaks down into a how
that is technical then there are others
who hear the what as maybe less
technical breaking even more technical
details so the details change but there
is a switch between being on the user
side which what is what's the product
and then the technical side is the
architect yeah so you made a distinction
there that I want to highlight for the
listeners between the what and the how
and I actually talk a lot when I give
talks on these topics about avoiding
jumping to how so that was interesting
you just talked about the what being the
non-technical and then the how being the
technical and if I heard you right you
said the architect is the first one who
takes the bridge from the non-technical
what which of course I'm I'm sure you'll
say they're also involved in helping
toine the non-technical what and then
mapping that to the technical how is
that did I hear that correctly yeah I
think the architect is off of the bridge
they really belong in both worlds they
really need to understand both worlds if
an architect doesn't understand the
business side of it or the product side
of it they won't be able to ask the
right questions so they will make the
jump to how so we all as humans I think
we have Tendencies to offer the solution
so when you talk to someone you tell
them what you want them to do and not
what problem you want them to
solve it's a standard thing right and
then when I have often conversations
with product people and it's not saying
anything about them it's just that they
would say okay so let's just do one two
three and problem solve and get go back
away but what is the problem we're
trying to solve and you have to
understand that problem because the
solution might be completely different
might be the same might be completely
different you won't have any way of
knowing without understanding the
problem so I think that really is the
bridge yeah in a prior conversation you
said something I thought was interesting
your statement was Architects are the
first response to product can you unpack
that a little bit
so from that understanding comes the
ability to arbitrate and mitigate
product requirements and whether they're
coming from a product professional
they're coming from customers clients or
Executives as it often happens in a
startup environment so if you have that
understanding of both sides you can be a
good arbitrator and you will understand
both sides you will say this is not
exactly what you're looking for I know
you said you want to add that feature
but I have a better proposition for you
I have another feature that I think will
solve your underlying problem that
you're trying to
solve and in that sense that buffer
between developers and nontechnical
people
if it's not there then I think a lot of
work
becomes I don't know if unnecessary but
I would say definitely Twisted in a
sense that it is defined not by
requirements and not by the problem but
by the solution absolutely in fact
Solutions coupled to
implementations in my experience is what
makes a lot of systems struggle because
if require requirements change and your
design is coupled to requirements then
every time requirements change your
design blows
up yeah of course requirements do change
and that's a good thing that's called
job
security but we complain about it
because our systems don't know how to
respond to change it's also kind of
human to respond poorly to change of
course I've worked on this for six
months why are you changing it now or
this is the way we've always done it
this is the way we've always done it why
do we need to change it and probably if
this is the way you've always done is
the best indication that you do need to
change it well see now again this is the
role of architect too where the
architect is not just arbitrating the
technical decisions but the architect is
also and maybe arbit mediating is maybe
a better word because arbitrating sounds
a little bit adversarial or facilitating
maybe also but also the personal side so
there's an architecture role on a
technical side but talk a little bit
more about like the old thing from the
office space right I just you know I'm
the product guy I take the requirements
from the customer to the developer
because I'm a pable person notice the
role that's missing there is the
architect so let's let's talk not that
that would have solved the problem of of
the the office and office space but what
is the role of architect from the
personal standpoint a little bit as far
as navigating that transition from
customer to requirements to development
it's a great question personally I think
you need the ability to make people see
your point but they not adversarial mhm
if you're adversarial then product won't
be able to work with you and then
they'll go around you and then you're
basically useless I'm sure there are
those architects who are just in it for
jumping I think you you kind of alluded
to that in the beginning just like
jumping from one thing to the other they
don't really want the accountability as
I said before I don't think that's
really the the common use case I agree
most Architects are Architects because
they care exactly and if you care you
have to so some people care too much at
certain points in my career I've cared
too much and I was like I I thought of
myself maybe as a gatekeeper instead of
a mediator and I think you said mediator
which is great there's a difference
between being a gatekeeper in IM mediate
I think at some point I thought of
myself as a gatekeeper meaning I should
keep bad requirements
away and as a medor you don't it's not
your I don't think it's your role to
keep bad requirements away it's your
role to
help whoever made those requirements
understand what are the right
requirements what are it's a good way to
put these requirements you know what's
brilliant about that too is if you know
something's a good idea but the other
person doesn't if you try to force it on
them they might resist but if they're
convinced that it was their idea
absolutely I think what you really meant
is that's how you lead them to it right
you say I heard you we can think about
that but I think what you really meant
was and go to the core of the issue or
have you thought about it this way oh
have you thought about it this way and
and let's figure out together basically
what we're all saying is let's figure
out together what is the problem but it
has to be together right so if you're
the kind of person that really doesn't
want
any interaction with other people or
with non-technical people and I I'm not
judging maybe that's not a role you need
to be well and that's a good point so
you know we started with the technical
aspects which of course we have you know
some time to dive into a little bit more
and and I want to on the technical side
but now we're kind of talking more about
the personal side which you could say is
the soft skills side right there's the
hard skills of being an architect the
technical and the design skills then
there's the soft skills side the process
and the people skills and so you know we
talk about the path of an architect and
you mentioned it before right they tend
to be the developer who maybe wants a
broader perspective or the engineer who
who sees the bigger picture and they
want to like lean into that a little bit
but none of that has given you soft
skills training so in your experience
where did you and where are successful
Architects Getting By the way soft
skills are not are
hard yeah right so where are they
getting that experience to be successful
on the people and process side of things
because they're often not trained in
that in my experience at least maybe
yours is different I have mentioned on
our previous conversation is that I came
in without the hard skills you came in
without the hard skills yes I came in
without the hard skills I came in with
the soft skill and I was learning on the
go learning the the the technical side
of it on the go I was always interested
in technology but I started actually as
a system architect system engineer
having came from the product side from
the business side of things and I was a
caring and uh passionate user and I was
interested in technology and that made
me a good candidate to be that
bridge and kind the soft skills come
from first they come from caring so if
we're talking about a specific domain
specific business domain then it may be
something that you're really passionate
about and you've experienced it as a
user and then you're able to explain
your passion and to talk to your passion
with others and you can talk to your
passion with others that are Technical
and others that are
non-technical and when you do they both
understand you because you've given a
lot of thought to yourself and then I
think I'm the wrong person to ask how to
be a people person I'm not sure I have a
people person but it's about
knowing that that's definitely something
you need right if you understand that
you need to be that person that
everybody comes to from the technical
side and from the nontechnical side and
if you want to be that person you will
be that person yeah and I guess part of
the challenge here is you and I both
came at this from the and maybe soft
skills isn't the only part of it from
the business side and then the technical
came later so that that's true for me as
well but we both know a lot of software
Architects as well and I'm curious to
your experience in my experience that's
the less common route the more common
route that I tend to see is people come
up through the technical side and then
they have to shore up or learn the soft
skills is that true for you as well most
of the time yeah absolutely and they
often struggle with that there you go so
now let's talk about that a little bit
because you know I'm sure you spend a
lot of time mentoring I do as well so
what do you do or what do you think a
software architect needs to do and can
do to shore up that side of their
ability to facilitate the interaction
between the business side and the
technical side I think often the first
thing they need is confidence because if
you're used to being part of a larger
team and you're individual contributor
but you're within very well defined
boundaries and then as an architect
those boundaries kind of fade away and
you talk to a lot more people and then
if you're not confident you get you
might get overwhelmed and then you might
get pushed back down back down into
where you feel comfortable or if govern
might be just writing code and you won't
be providing that service of being that
bridge it's got being that mediator so I
spend time with when I'm mentoring is
building confidence just you know this
you know both sides you've been at this
long enough and you share about it
enough and have enough passion about it
to be able to talk about the subject
with anyone and with that confidence the
shyness or the apprehension Fades away I
think that really confidence really is
key and by the way the psychology tell
us one of the best ways to build
confidence is to act confident because
you get the feedback loop because when
you act confident people perceive you as
confident and then you perceive them
perceiving you as confident then you
become confident of course the opposite
is true if you don't appear confident
people perceive you as not confident you
perceive that they perceive is not
confident and then you're not confident
and then you withdraw yeah and that's a
simplistic way of looking at it but it's
part of the equation so building
confidence but what else because there
are those occasional Architects too who
are incredibly confident and they're
really good at like beating people down
with their strong technical opinions so
and I know you're not saying that and
let's not really go too much there but I
just want to tell listeners that's not
what we're saying you know you're not
saying be confident like that person
you're saying reasonable confidence in
somebody who the confidence will benefit
them and it will benefit others not
because they're trying to browbeat
people but because they do have good
contributions to make and if they're not
confident then they're not going to be
able to participate I don't want to get
too deep into psychology because I'm not
I'm not a professional but I don't cons
these people actually confident people
who need to BR it doesn't come from a
place of confidence yeah like bullies
are actually afraid a lot of times right
yeah I I think so I mean it takes a lot
more confidence and self assurance to
listen than to yell at others and force
your opinion on others that's what I was
looking for exactly that's a great
summary of that so let's move off of
confidence for a minute what else like
so I have confidence that's like an
attribute but are there any specific
skills from a soft skills side that you
find that software Architects benefit
from when they have these particular
kinds of skills from the personal and
the process side the people side I just
kind of touched on that without even
noticing you have to be a good listener
because you need to listen to the
problems people bring to you I think
people come to the architect from both
sides we said before people's from
people from the technical side people
from the business side and then you have
to listen to all of them because you
don't know the questions or the answers
better than anyone
you might be the best at translating
them that would be another skill so the
ability to translate between Technical
and non-technical and translate between
people I've often been in that scenario
where I have uh non- technical person
and a developer on a call and they
really don't understand each other and
they're both good people but you have to
listen you have to understand that
they're not understand in each other and
you have to be the mediator and speak a
Common Language and speaking common
language is very difficult soft skill to
master I'm not sure anybody ever Masters
it all the way because it it changes
based on your business if you switch
from one business to the other but there
are some commonalities and I think the
the one thing that you can notice
regardless of what business you're in is
that two other people are not speaking
the same language and once you do that's
the first step into getting them to
speak the same language or at least you
translating between them so that they
can yeah that's fine that's fine
hopefully you don't have to translate
everything you can facilitate it you can
start the conversation and then they
will understand each other well and it's
tough too because you point out if you
notice they don't understand each other
the reality is they may think they
understand each other and then you have
to to show them that they
don't and you have to do it gently yes
you have to make them see it without
spelling it out because then people
become uncomfortable and then they
become withdrawn and then they feel
misunderstood and people don't like
feeling misund that's true Switching
gears a little bit I feel like we're
getting a broad picture you know there's
some soft skills there's some hard
skills technical people skills these
kinds of things for a software architect
but give us just briefly a picture of
what does a successful software
architect look like and then let's talk
about what are the challenges that keep
Architects from feeling like they're
able to have that consistent success in
their role what's hold what's maybe
holding them back either in themselves
or or in the systems that they're
working in if we assume that the
architect in question is the type of
architect that does want to take
accountability over software design
throughout the life cycle of an
application then a successful architect
will be one that can maintain a vision
of what architect architecture should be
and what design should be and
influence how it is done over time so
the design vision is consistent over
time well consistent sounds kind of
strict like it shouldn't change it can
change it should adapt but it should be
done done through the architect's eyes
from top down and not from bottom up so
maybe it's the design vision is
consistently curated over time oh yeah I
like that okay I like that okay so a
successful architect is able to
consistently curate the design and the
design Vision over the life cycle of the
project even more than that I think what
I would be like to be measured on as an
architect is my ability through that
design through that VIs to facilitate
software development to facilitate to
enable the creations of new features new
Integrations and the right ones right
not just new for the sake of new but the
right features and
Integrations okay so let's try this so a
successful software architect helps
developers
successfully deliver on the actual
requirements something like that maybe
yeah that's good on the requirements are
based on the root problems the core
issues we're trying to resolve right
real requirements real requirements yeah
yes okay so that's a successful software
architect and I I love that because we
help make everybody better right we help
the developers be better we help the
product be better we help them solve the
problems we understand the real problems
and we provide real solutions that solve
the actual real problem great what's
holding us
back well I think there are things
holding us back on multiple levels
there's the organizational level that
the sometimes it looks like the design
phase or the Lector of is a good thing
we we don't need it's just we are
spending time on design why are we
spending time on design we should just
go and write Solutions start
iterating yeah and I get Dilbert in my
head right we all know the the Dilbert
type manager and I'm not saying that all
executives are like that absolutely not
I've worked with amazing exective I
actually never worked with executive
like that but it's still kind of their
job saying let's get this done as fast
as we can and you need to understand as
an architect and convince others that as
fast as we
can at least over time does mean with
good design and the proper amount of
time spent on design and that's a
difficult thing to do it's difficult to
as they say talk truth to power and it's
difficult task to convince people that
are measured on time delivery why
something could take 10% or 15% longer
now but over time even if everything
takes 15% longer it won't get delayed
100% in the next interation right we
won't get stuck because we didn't think
it over we didn't plan ahead so that's a
real difficult task and I think that's
one reason why Architects are
struggling another reason would be
coming from the the technical side is
that with a lot of ownership moving down
to team leaders over time which I think
is a good thing then it became kind of
contentious into who is the owner and
why are you telling me what to do and of
course in a good relationship right it's
not nobody is telling anybody what to do
but it's not often the case and so from
the executive side may be say we don't
need this space it just takes time from
the technical side they might say well
I'm doing the design you're getting in
my way but that team lead have a very
much narrower scope and they're maybe
doing good design but on their narrow
scope and then the architect which
should have the broader scope he doesn't
have the backing from the executives and
he doesn't have the team leader going up
to him saying I need your help and if in
neither of these things happen then they
can't be successful and then on top of
that the architect's role I think
throughout at least my history
has been very much tied into
documentation and I don't mean comments
in code necessarily but documentation
generally is writing documents and
drawing
diagrams and then maintaining those over
time and you spend a lot of time on
maintaining I used to spend I used to
have a spreadsheet with a a huge huge
data datase specification like SQL
database relational database
specification with every public key and
foreign key
documented and it would take half my
time just to manage that with change
requirements and it doesn't have the
ability to impose that on the actual
implementation nor does it get updated
with the with the actual implementation
so you're just doing
documentation kind of for your sake
and so with everything else being
automated and we don't have those tools
yet and it feels kind of a caic in some
way it does an analogy that comes to my
mind that I use a lot is if my water
heater breaks and I need to call a
technician and they show up and the
water heater itself doesn't have a
document you know attached inside it or
they can't go online and find a document
for the specification they are going to
going to struggle to figure out how to
fix this water heater because there's no
specification of how the thing is
intended to work and how it does in fact
work or washing machine or figure
anything out and yet with software we
often just say well just look at
it like yeah but looking at it doesn't
tell you the intent of the purpose and
the design and these kinds of things
right right and so we have to resolve
the conflict between what we designed
and what we document and what is
actually happening and we have to keep
doing that all the time and that just
takes a a lot of our time and often also
becomes a reason for conflict you'll go
to developer saying wait we designed it
like this why did you implement it like
that and then there's a lot of
contention well and that's where I think
coming up from documentation for a
minute you said something before you
said you know how do we you didn't use
exact same words but instead of quick
and dirty it was how do we do quick and
clean like and how do we maintain that
consistently and I I put documentation
in that category of and somebody asked
what's the right amount of documentation
I said well there it is it's the answer
that we can keep going quick and clean
we're not slowing down because we don't
know what the heck we built right and
then there's other things you mentioned
too I think you didn't use the word but
you're also talking about constraints
you sort of hearkened to the idea of
constraints so talk a little bit about
yourist systems engineer as well so you
know constraints like triggers a whole
bunch of thoughts I'm sure in your mind
talk a little bit about the software
architect's role as it pertains to
constraints within the software system
and the human systems around it well I
think it's all constraints because if
there were new constraints we could all
just wish a software would do something
and it would magically do that that'd be
amazing yeah and even with Gen we're
very far from that I think that the
constraints come in all levels so there
are constraints on the availability of
Engineers and the availability of their
engineering knoow and then of course
there are constraints on performance and
so if you will build a very your design
sorry a very different application if
you have a requirement to deliver
responses within a minute or a second or
a millisecond and that is often a very
hard constraint
because no person is an island and no
software is an island definitely not in
our world you're always getting
information from other softwares and
possibly producing information for
others and then you might just be
getting a
million bytes a million megabytes per
second terabyte per second a petabyte
per petabyte might be extended to too
much but you might be getting terabytes
per minute and then that's a real
constraint there's nothing you can't
negotiate there you have to work with it
and then on the other side you need to
provide something to the user but you
can do that within a minute and then you
have all that time in the middle to
figure out what the right thing to do so
these are the parameters of the problems
you're solving the constraint of the
parameters everything is an optimization
prop right it's just the constraint is
what you optimize to without that I
would you as an architect I don't know
where to start right without somebody
telling me the parameters of a problem
where would I start with a solution
absolutely and you you mentioned what
you optimize for is the constraint and
for those who aren't familiar with that
phrase that's straight out of systems
engineering so another area that I think
often holds software Architects and the
systems that we designed back is quality
we've talked about constraints we've
talked about some other other aspects of
this but if you will speak some to how
quality relates to the role of software
architect in your experience well that's
that's actually it's written right here
in my notes how it's one of the roles of
the architect I wanted to to discuss
because I think quality means a lot of
things to a lot of people and the word
quality you have quality assurance and I
don't think that's that's not that type
of quality you have code quality and I
actually don't think that's that either
I think there is a engineering quality
or maybe the quality of of an
application of the design of the
software it's its own thing and quality
is the ability to understand something
to for it to make sense in a way that
you can then continue working on it
right if if the quality isn't there then
you don't have anything to build on so
if you want to if you have imagine a a
Breck house you stack bricks one top the
other and if the bricks are from poor
quality at some point with some amount
of weight they'll crumble and then
everything goes down so quality is the
basis of what you're building on and if
the software quality is something that
is through good practices something we
can we can achieve right something we
can actively work on and improve it's
not a binary it's not a zero1 but it's
something we can always improve on so
that when you get started you make the
right decisions in your also in your
practices if you the right decision may
be to make sure that
everybody has a cicd that includes
testing for example right you might not
think that's not the first thing you
think about is a role of an architect
but I think it really is something that
the architect should care about about
how people interact with their software
right with their if if I'm a team lead
and I'm very technical person I just
want to write code and more features and
more features and somebody has to tell
me wait wait a minute stop let's make
sure that the new feature you wrote
didn't break everything else so it's not
as much a design decision it's a
decision to make sure that there is
something to build on it's another
design constraint really you're
constrained by the quality of your
system and if you want to get past those
constraints you may need higher quality
in some cases you have to manage quality
and you have to do that and it could be
something that an engineering executive
does especially if they are passionate
Engineers themselves but it might not be
and I think it's definitely part of the
role to make sure that these kind of
standards and practices are met so you
have something to build on yeah and if
you go back to Edward Deming who I'll
put some notes in the show notes about
Edward Deming who's the father of total
quality management you mentioned quality
management and for those of you who are
involved in in things like lean if you
haven't read about Edward Deming and the
Toyota miracle from the 1950s you
absolutely owe it to yourself to do that
because while quality as you're saying
is part of the software architect's job
as you learn about tqm it's everybody's
job it's just an architect has a
specific part and role to play in that
what other aspects of the software
architect's role did you have in mind
that you want to make sure we cover in
the time we have left anything else you
wanted to highlight so maybe one thing
we haven't really discussed is being the
facilitator of change and being open for
change think maybe we've kind of talked
around it but being
open-minded and making sure that you
don't just say no it's a very Gutt
response there's somebody asking you
something you just say no that's not
what it should how it should be or
that's not how we do it and I think you
need to be as an architect if you own
the design and if the design is good it
needs to be very
Dynamic uh static design will break you
know they they say that the bridge that
collapses is the bridge that doesn't
move with the wind so I think that's
exactly the case if you own the design
design isn't Dynamic then it will break
you won't be able to build on it and you
have to do that so you need to actively
seek change you need to actively see how
you can improve if you've designed
something a year ago and you're you are
the owner of the design of that
application you have to revisit what the
application does today you have to
revisit what the software requirements
are and how they've changed and the
design you made a year ago which may
have been correct a year ago it might
not be the right design now yeah last
year I'll put a link in the show notes
to a prior episode with Chad Michael
from Don't Panic labs and the title was
software is an engineering discipline
but in his book on the topic he has a
phrase that I really appreciate it's
design for a change in fact I think I
even said it earlier in the episode so
now I'm just giving credit what credit
is due and so that's really the Holy
Grail right where we can design for a
change and we know our designs might
change but if they keep changing
constantly fundamentally in their
because you know it's interesting you
mentioned the bridge well the reason the
bridge is dynamic and can stand up to
the wind is because of how the bridge
was designed yes so it's it's good
design that lets you accommodate change
absolutely it's good design that lets
you accommodate change
so you can think of the bridge analogy
as both Sid the wind being the change
requirements and the design being the
actual design yeah similar to buildings
right if you want a building to stand up
in an earthquake old school thinking
would have been it doesn't move it's
immovable and now if you if you look at
the Dynamics of how buildings that can
tolerate earthquakes are they're
extremely flexible and dynamic it's
amazing so the design is flexible
because the wind will come if I close my
eyes and close my ears the wind won't
come it will come right it won't help
bury our heads in the sand and just hope
yeah that that won't help you can do
that if you're a software architect I
hope that's not what you're doing
exactly so in the time we have left I
know that you work for a company called
V function and there are some things
that your company provides that are
intended to help Architects be better at
doing their job so talk a little bit
about V function and what you guys do to
help make software Architects lives
better great so we provide architectural
observability to basically provide
insights into complex software and we
enable developers engineers and
especially Architects to understand the
architecture of the software enabling
them to continuously manage their
technical Deb and modernize their
application and modernize continuously
modernized application which is exactly
what I was alluding for to before having
the design being a living breeding thing
that needs to be updated as the
application changes the new prod change
you said something interesting as you
were describing V function and what it
provides you've called it architecture
observability so since this is an audio
only show and we can't show pictures to
the listeners if you can try to paint a
picture for us about what could somebody
expect if they had a solution that
provides them architecture observability
well I think a lot of it goes down to
dependency management and dependencies
could be between classes in a software
or between database tables or code and
database and then external Services
could be some cloud provider service and
really anything could be dependent on
pretty much anything else within the
Software System complex system is a
system system where these dependencies
are complex right and there may be
circular and there may be some
dependencies are shared very liberally
throughout While others very localized
which is often the best case right local
we like localized dependencies localized
dependencies hinted modularity which is
something we aspire to and so the first
thing we do is we visualize these
dependencies and visualizing these
dependencies with the context
and the context being the domains the
business domains within a software with
application and then allowing you to
make
decisions on which of these
dependencies belong and are correct and
which of these dependencies are ones you
really want to get rid
of and then over time really showing you
when new dependencies are added and any
specific areas of Interest right because
there are two aspects here one is
visualizing and then there is
prioritizing because you don't want to
get overwhelmed you need to be Predators
so you some input may be coming from the
user us saying I'm interested in this
part of the software right now I'm going
to put effort into making it better
because it's really hurting me I'm
feeling the pain from trying to develop
new features within a certain domain so
let's focus on that and it could be
coming from the system saying this class
is gone it's in god mode right it's a
god class we don't want that it's every
time you touch anything you need to
change this glass so you need to fix it
and so visualizing these dependencies
and pointing them out to the architect
and prioritizing that's really what the
observ identifying them visualizing them
priority iing
them well Ori it's been great having you
on the show is there anything else you
want to cover in the time we have left
before we wrap it up no really like to
thank you Jeff really like spending this
time with you talking about software
architecture yeah it was great having
you on the show if listeners want to
find out more about what you're up to
where can they go online well they can
go to they can find me on LinkedIn and
they can go to v function.com v
function.com that's the word function
with the v in front.com yes fantastic
well Orie thank you so much for being a
guest on software engineering radio
thank you Jeff this is Jeff dittle
thanks for joining us see you
later thanks for listening to SC radio
and educational program brought to you
by It software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening